So I thought, "I will talk about death."
اذا، أعتقدت أنني، "سأتحدث عن الموت."
Seemed to be the passion today.
يبدو أنه المنشود اليوم
Actually, it's not about death.
حقيقةً، ليس الموضوع عن الموت
It's inevitable, terrible, but really what I want to talk about is,
رغم أنه لا مفر منه، رهيب، لكن ما أريد الحديث عنه في الواقع
I'm just fascinated by the legacy people leave when they die.
أنا مفتونة بالتركة التي يخلفها الناس بعد موتهم
That's what I want to talk about.
هذا ما أريد الحديث عنه
So Art Buchwald left his legacy of humor with a video
اذا ترك آرت بوشوالد ورثته الفكاهية في الفيديو
that appeared soon after he died, saying,
الذي ظهر بعد وفاته بقليل، يقول،
"Hi! I'm Art Buchwald, and I just died."
مرحباً! "أنا آرت بوشوالد، ولقد مت للتو."
And Mike, who I met at Galapagos, a trip which I won at TED,
ومايك، الذي ألتقيته في جالاباقوس، الرحلة التي فزت بها في TED
is leaving notes on cyberspace where he is chronicling
يترك مذكرات في الإنترنت حيث يؤرخ
his journey through cancer.
رحلته مع مرض السرطان
And my father left me a legacy of his handwriting
وترك لي والدي ميراث من خط يده
through letters and a notebook.
عبر الخطابات والمذكرات
In the last two years of his life, when he was sick,
في آخر سنتين من حياته، عندما كان مريضاً
he filled a notebook with his thoughts about me.
لقد ملأ مذكرته بخواطره عني
He wrote about my strengths, weaknesses,
كتب عن مكامن قوتي، نقاط ضعفي،
and gentle suggestions for improvement,
وبعض النصائح اللطيفة للتطوير
quoting specific incidents, and held a mirror to my life.
نقلاً عن حوادث معينة ، وحمل مرآة لحياتي
After he died, I realized that no one writes to me anymore.
وبعد موته، أدركت أنه لا أحد يكتب لي بعد الآن
Handwriting is a disappearing art.
الكتابة باليد فن يختفي
I'm all for email and thinking while typing,
الجميع بصدد البريد الإلكتروني، والتفكير أثناء الطباعة
but why give up old habits for new?
لكن لماذا نضحيّ بالعادات القديمة من أجل الجديدة؟
Why can't we have letter writing and email exchange in our lives?
لماذا لا نستطيع كتابة خطابات وتبادل البريد الإلكتروني في حياتنا؟
There are times when I want to trade all those years
مرّت أوقات أردت مقايضة كل تلك السنوات
that I was too busy to sit with my dad and chat with him,
التي كنت مشغولة عن والدي والدردشة معه
and trade all those years for one hug.
أردت مقايضة كل تلك السنوات بحضن واحد
But too late.
ولكن بعد فوات الأوان.
But that's when I take out his letters and I read them,
لكن عندما أخرج الرسائل وأقرأها
and the paper that touched his hand is in mine,
والأوراق التي لامست يديه تخصني
and I feel connected to him.
وأحس بأنني متصلة به
So maybe we all need to leave our children
لذا ربما سنحتاج ترك لأولادنا
with a value legacy, and not a financial one.
ميراث قيّم، وليس ثروة مالية
A value for things with a personal touch --
أشياء قيمة بلمسة شخصية--
an autographed book, a soul-searching letter.
كتاب توقيعات، رسالة بحث عن النفس
If a fraction of this powerful TED audience
اذا أمكن عدد قليل من حضور TED الفاعل
could be inspired to buy a beautiful paper --
بالإستلهام وشراء ورقة جميلة--
John, it'll be a recycled one -- and write a beautiful letter
جون، ستكون معادة التصنيع-- ويكتبوا رسالة جميلة
to someone they love, we actually may start a revolution
لشخص ما يحبونه، حقيقةً ربما نبدأ ثورة
where our children may go to penmanship classes.
حيث ربما يذهب أطفالنا الى فصول لدراسة فن الخط
So what do I plan to leave for my son?
اذا ما أخطط له لأجل ولدي؟
I collect autographed books, and those of you authors
أجمع كتب التوقيعات، وتلك التي لكم أنتم المؤلفون
in the audience know I hound you for them --
في معرفة ولع الجمهور بهم
and CDs too, Tracy.
والأقراص الصلبة أيضاً، تريسي
I plan to publish my own notebook.
أخطط لنشر مذكراتي الخاصة
As I witnessed my father's body being swallowed by fire,
حينما راقبت جسد والدي تلتهمه النيران
I sat by his funeral pyre and wrote.
جلست بالقرب من محرقة جنازته وكتبت
I have no idea how I'm going to do it,
لم تكن لدي فكرة عن كيفية فعل ذلك
but I am committed to compiling his thoughts and mine
لكني ملتزمة بترجمة أفكاره وأفكاري
into a book, and leave that published book for my son.
في كتاب، وترك ذلك الكتاب المنشور لولدي
I'd like to end with a few verses of what I wrote
أريد أن أختم بقليل من الإقتباسات مما كتبته
at my father's cremation.
في محرقة جنازة والدي
And those linguists, please pardon the grammar,
وبالنسبة لمتخصصي اللغات ، أرجوكم أنتبهوا للقواعد
because I've not looked at it in the last 10 years.
لأنني لم أراعيها خلال العشر سنين الماضية
I took it out for the first time to come here.
أقدمها لكم لأول مرة هنا
"Picture in a frame, ashes in a bottle,
"صورة في إطار، رماد في زجاجة،
boundless energy confined in the bottle,
طاقة لا محدودة تُحبس في زجاجة،
forcing me to deal with reality,
تجبرني على القبول بالواقع
forcing me to deal with being grown up.
تجبرني على تقبّل أنني أصبحت ناضجة
I hear you and I know that you would want me to be strong,
أسمعك وأعرف أنك تريدني أن أكون قوية
but right now, I am being sucked down, surrounded
لكن الآن، أنا منجذبة الى الأسفل، محاصرة،
and suffocated by these raging emotional waters,
ومختنقة عاطفياً بهذه المياة الهائجة
craving to cleanse my soul, trying to emerge
شغوفة بتطهير روحي، تحاول الخروج
on a firm footing one more time, to keep on fighting and flourishing
على أساس متين مرة أخرى، لمواصلة النضال والإزدهار
just as you taught me.
تماماً كما علمتني
Your encouraging whispers in my whirlpool of despair,
رسالتك المشجعة لي في دوامتي مع اليأس
holding me and heaving me to shores of sanity,
إمساكي وأخذي الى ضفاف الإستقامة،
to live again and to love again."
للعيش مجدداً والحب مجدداً."
Thank you.
شكراً لكم